Yuri Dolzhneko

Tech lead / Full stack software engineer

Born 19 December, 1984

Nationality: Dutch

Fritz Dietrich Kahlenbergstraat, 133 | 1087 LL, Amsterdam | The Netherlands

+31 (o) 634883558 | yuri.dolzhenko@gmail.com

Summary

Tech lead / full stack software engineer with about 12 years of experience in designing, developing and maintaining software solutions for various businesses and customers.

Buzzwords

Software design and architecture, team leading and coaching. Lots of Java and JVM languages on a backend. Legacy systems, microservices, monoliths, refactoring of those. RESTful and GraphQL APIs. Spring framework and everything that comes with it. Data centers on premises, AWS and Pivotal Cloud Foundry. A bit of data analytics using mapreduce, R and some other fancy tools. SQL or NOSQL databases - both may work, depending on a task to solve. Angular, Typescript, D3.js, Ext JS for creating user interfaces SPAs, PWAs or mobile applications. NPM, Maven, Gradle for managing dependencies and building things. Atlassian tools for managing projects and knowledge sharing. Git for version control, Jenkins, CircleCI and GitLab for continuous integration and delivery, Docker for portability and predictability, Kubernetes - for running things and scale them up and down. Sonar, JUnit, Mockito, Karma, Jasmine, Selenium to make sure things are reliable. Reactive and functional programming for efficiency and performance. Agile, scrum and devops for making this list complete.

Experience

• 2018 - present, KLM Royal Dutch Airlines, (http://www.klm.nl), The Netherlands

Tech lead

I came to KLM as a consultant/senior full stack engineer and joined a team that worked on building software tools and solutions on demand by internal customers across the whole company - we had projects for cargo department, we helped planning department with schedule and rostering for cockpit/cabin crews, we provided the means for monitoring disruptions and visualizing data for engine maintenance. These solutions are

meant to be built quickly from scratch in a truly agile manner, meaning we discuss problems with customers, we design a solution and build it in a way that users can start using them ASAP, while providing us with feedback about usage patterns and new requirements. We use Spring Boot to build backends, Angular/Ionic to build user interfaces, we save data mostly to PostreSQL, we consume many other internal data sources, both very legacy and new ones. We deploy our software in Pivotal Cloud Foundry or on in-house Kubernetes cluster. Eventually I took the role of techincal lead of the team and joined KLM as internal employee. Currently besides development itself I'm responsible for coaching team members, short and long term planning of development work and discussing requirements with our old and new (happy) customers.

• 2017 - 2018, Randstad, (http://www.randstad.nl), The Netherlands

Senior full stack developer, Consultant

In Randstad, I helped the company with migration of its software from the on-premises data centers to the AWS. The goal was not only to lift things and move them to another infrastructure, but plan, create a foundation and eventually make applications cloud-native, so we could benefit from all tools AWS offers. We had lots of different frontends, apis and applications that use all sorts of technologies and frameworks - some of them were old and ready to retire, some used RDBMS, some - NOSQL, so strategic planning was essential. While migrating we still had to develop new features and maintain ones, and migration itself had been done as seamlessly as possible without customers and business people noticing anything.

• 2017 - 2020, LinkIT, (http://www.linkit.nl), The Netherlands

Consultant

I joined LinkIT, another consultancy company to participate in efforts to transform a typical consultancy bureau into enterprise that combines traditional staffing and consultancy services with in-house development of solutions for clients.

• 2014 - 2017, ING, (http://www.ing.nl), The Netherlands

Senior full stack developer, Consultant

As a full stack developer I joined ING bank's new omni-channel initiative (in a nutshell - same API endpoints serving data for all types of clients, from self-service portals for private and business customers to call centers and bank'

branches). RESTful APIs (based on Spring and in-house built frameworks) that we built were bridges between modern frontends (web/mobile) and TIBCO messaging infrastructure that was connected with bank's legacy systems and mainframes. I was part of one of many cross functional feature-teams (squads, as bank tried to adopt Spotify model) consisted of everybody necessary to design, build, deploy (on in-house hardware), monitor and support (we had 24/7 support for some of the apis) fully-functional solutions.

• 2014 - 2017, Qualogy, (http://www.qualogy.nl), The Netherlands

Consultant

After three years of working on the same product, I felt like I had enough of regulatory reporting and was ready for something different. I joined Qualogy as a consultant in 2014 to have an opportunity to work for different clients, face different problems and see what's going on in industry as I started to feel that I got stuck and began to lag behind.

• **2011** - **2014**, Secondfloor (www.secondfloor.com), The Netherlands

Java developer

I had never thought about moving to the Netherlands, but nevertheless it happened suddenly. One of many Dutch recruitment companies reached me at LinkedIn and asked if I was interested in having an interview with one of theirs clients. «Why not?» - I replied. After a couple of talks I found myself packing my stuff and buying one-way ticket to Amsterdam. Company was all about risk and regulatory reporting solutions for insurance and finance companies. There I worked on a product jointly created by us and IBM - requirements were coming from IBM, we were working on the implementation and later on IBM was selling the final product to their customers. It was a tool that was used for collection of structured and unstructured data, that was used for reporting and decision making. Application was Spring-backed (MVC, security, JMS messaging) and connected to Oracle or DB2 databases (using Hibernate for the most things and plain JDBC for some of them). It exposed a set of RESTful APIs for third-parties and for our own frontend that was built using Ext JS. We had a team of one project manager who did all the planning, three to seven developers to actually develop what was planned, couple of testers to test things and business analyst who was busy with writing specifications together with analysts

from IBM. I worked on both backend and frontend parts of the application and was involved with anything that was on the table: implementing features, maintaining quality, preparing releases and supporting our customers.

• 2009-2011, Luxoft (http://www.luxoft.ru/), Russia

Senior java developer, lead java developer

Luxoft was (and, I guess, still is) one the biggest IT consultancy companies in eastern Europe, with the solid portfolio of clients such as Boeing, Deutsche Bank and UBS. I failed first interview there when I first came to Moscow and succeeded one year later. I joined one of the many development teams that company had on-site at UBS bank. We worked on application that was essentially a frontend to multiple bank's datasources with information about financial instruments. We had to replace old swing-based desktop solution that was slow and unreliable with the new, webbased one (spring mvc, with freemarker templates and Jquery / Jquery UI on the frontend). We had four developers (based in Moscow), testing team in Bangalore, India and product owner in Boston, USA. We maintained and supported four instances of the application in four different regions across the world (long before AWS showed up) and that guaranteed us lots of fun when it came to communication: catch up calls/meetings in the evenings because of Boston's time zone, bunches of issues every morning from our QA team in Bangalore and issues from our users at any random point in time. While working on the project, my responsibilities grew from housekeeping and bug fixing to developing new features and later to releases management, supporting customers and planning changes upfront.

• 2008-2009, Intouch Insurance (http://www.intouch.ru), Russia

Java developer

I moved to Moscow in pursuit of career opportunities - there weren't many things to do in my hometown. I immediately joined in-house development team of "Intouch Insurance", a back-then pioneer company in selling and managing insurance policies entirely online with no front offices whatsoever. Company was part of the international insurance group, so team was distributed between Moscow and Warsaw - so a lot of traveling, remote work and communication were involved. We were responsible for building, customizing and maintaining internal CRM system based on Sapiens IDITSuite which covered

all the business processes that are typical for insurance companies - policy sales, claims handling, payments management and etc. We had a pretty much typical web-based setup for those days - huge monolithic application, JSPs, Struts servlets, Java EE's JDO to connect to Oracle database and a tiny bit of javascript on a frontend side.

• 2007-2008, Rostelecom (http://www.rostelecom.ru/), Russia

Java developer

I started my software engineering career in the biggest Russian telecommunications company. There I worked in a department responsible for a bunch of intranet applications used by company's different departments (HR, billing, etc). RPCs instead of RESTful APIs, Struts instead of Spring, pure JDBC instead of object-relational mapping tools, no continuous deployment or delivery. No Jira, agile, test driven development or devops. We were responsible for everything starting from initial design to deployments and users support and there were no buzz words invented to describe our way of working just yet.

Education & certification

- 2001-2006, Mathematician, system programmer, master degree (Kuban State University, Krasnodar, Russia)
- 2012, MongoDB Developer (10 Gen training & certification)
- *2013, Certified Spring Professional (VMWare training & certification)
- 2018, AWS Certified Solutions Architect Associate (Amazon Web Services)